<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>SCRUM CARD GAME</title>
    <subtitle>The Manual</subtitle>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Timofey (Tim)</firstname>
          <surname>Yevgrashyn</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <personname>
          <firstname>Oliver</firstname>
          <surname>Merkel</surname>
        </personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2010, 2016</year>
      <holder>Timofey (Tim) Yevgrashyn, All rights reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <releaseinfo>Version 3.1, July 2016, see http://scrumcardgame.com for updates and additional materials.</releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>SCRUM CARD GAME by Timofey (Tim) Yevgrashyn is licensed under a Creative Commons
        Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</para>
      <para>You have permission to use, copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format
        and also remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even
        commercially.</para>
      <para>Under the following terms:</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Attribution</emphasis> — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and
        indicate if changes were made.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">ShareAlike</emphasis> — If you remix, transform, or build upon the material, you must distribute your
        contributions under the same license as the original.</para>
      <para>To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0.</para>
      <para>All logos, brands, and trademarks mentioned belong to their respective owners.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <chapter>
    <title>SCRUM CARD GAME rules</title>

    <section>
      <title>What is SCRUM CARD GAME?</title>

      <para>SCRUM CARD GAME is a simple game, which lets players experience work in Scrum sprints
        and brings to discussion many questions and topics that happen in real life while working
        in a Scrum team. Even the discussion on the table will be very close to the real-life
        experience of the work in a scrum team. This game is usually played during a training or
        workshop. Participants must already have an understanding of the Scrum framework. Or
        you should introduce them to the framework right before the game. They can learn more
        while playing this game. It might also be a useful method to make an experienced team
        reflect on their established scrum rituals and rules.</para>
      <para>Split the audience into teams of 4-5-6 people, equally if
        possible. No more than six players per team.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Objective</title>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Set the Goal: You are competitive development centers aimed to deliver a new
        application to the market. The most productive team wins :-)</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Game Material</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="130mm" fileref="media/game_material_de.jpg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>The main Scrum Card Game components.</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>The game set consists of</para>
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Set of cards: Stories, Events, Problems, and Solutions (see printable version below)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Two six-sided dice (per each team)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Flipchart
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Markers or Post-Its
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Preparation</title>
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
        <listitem>
          <para>Provide each team with a set of Story cards
            <itemizedlist mark='opencircle'>
              <listitem>
                <para>Cards with stories forming the “Backlog” deck</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Backlog is prioritized (sequence number in top corner) and estimated
                 (hours in bottom corner)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>3 days per iteration (there will be maximum 3 iterations)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Every iteration consists of:
                  <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Planning and commitment</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Work within iteration</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Sprint Review + Retrospective</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make the group arrange a simple Task Board by marking TODO, IN PROGRESS,
            DONE columns with simple sticky notes to visualize their state.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Prepare a flipchart list with visualization of PLAN and ACTUAL columns for each
            team in play.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Planning</title>
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
        <listitem>
          <para>Ask teams “how many features do you believe you can deliver in the next
            iteration?”
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
              <listitem>
                <para>In the first round let every team calculate their number of man-hours per
                  iteration as they would like to do.
                  Allow them to make even optimistic commitment :)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>To perform 2nd and 3rd planning you ask teams to use historical data.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Put selected cards from “Backlog” into TODO column.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Write down commitment as the total number of estimates and numbers of Stories
            of every team on a flip chart into “Plan” column.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Daily Work within an Iteration</title>
      <para>Each iteration consists of three days. Each day consists of every
        team-member working on the sprint. It starts with player 1 “working”
        on the sprint. If the last member of the team “worked” the first day
        has ended. Now the same for day two and three starts. “Working” in the
        sprint is described below. Every team member in their turn should:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select a Story to work on (it should appear in “IN PROGRESS”) and make this
            choice visible by pointing on the card with the finger.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Roll two dice to determine the number of productive hours of
            this team-member on this day
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
              <listitem>
                <para>Hand over two dice on the first round right after explaining this step.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Deduct number on the dice from remaining hours on the card (s)he “works on”
○ Advise players to calculate remaining as it helps to avoid mistakes
○ To simplify tracking participants can stick a post-it on a card and write
remaining time there
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Pull the card from the “Chance” deck
○ Hand over the “Chance” deck on the first round right after explaining this
step
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Do whatever the card says. There are three possible types of cards:
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Event</emphasis> - a one-time
                  action, that affects immediately and is discarded after
                  being played.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Problem</emphasis> - these sticky
                  issues are blocking the Story that the player was
                  “working on”. Each problem is a case taken from the real
                  life, a team could bring examples or details into each
                  Problem from their experience.
                  <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Blocking means the team can’t move the story
                        into DONE state, they have to find a Solution for
                        the kind of problems stated on a card.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Blocking doesn’t prevent from continue work
                        on a Story (deducting hours until zero).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Sometimes, positive Events could also
                        help with Problems :-)</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Solution</emphasis> - A solution
                  is a team’s asset or action which can be applied at
                  any time to solve a problem and unblock a Story. Once
                  a Solution is applied the Problem and Solution card
                  are both discarded.
                  <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Solutions could be collected by the team if there
                        are no appropriate Problems - they are collected from
                        iteration to iteration and belong to the whole team.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If User Story is done (0 hours remaining and no blockers) -
            move it to DONE column.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>DONE criteria for a Story:
            <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
              <listitem>
                <para>Team members delivered the number of hours equal or
                  greater than the estimate of the Story.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>A Story must not be blocked by a Problem.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Once again, at every “day” each player does follow:
        <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
          <listitem>
            <para>Choose a card to “work on”</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Throw two dice</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Pick a Chance card</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Sprint Review + Retrospective</title>
      <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
        <listitem>
          <para>After each player's 3rd turn the Sprint is over.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Each team should present Stories accomplished (i.e. only
            stories in DONE column) and calculate the actual result as the
            total of DONE Stories.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Compare Actual result with initial Plan.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Review remaining work and discuss the reason, also discuss
            how to account these remaining Stories in next Sprint to make
            sure we maintain the total number from the original
            estimations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Retrospect on how to perform in next Sprint to achieve more.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Debriefing</title>
      <para>To start debriefing you should bring the flipchart(s) in front of the
        audience to visualize all Planned and Actual data for each of the three
        sprints. Here are some topics to adress
        <itemizedlist mark='bullet'>
          <listitem>
            <para>Planned vs. Actual</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Velocity variations</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Hours Estimate vs. Size (Original Estimate)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Major risks happened (technical, people, unplanned Events)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>What are the hardest types of risks to take?</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Could we forecast bad events?</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>etc…</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Get the Game Materials</title>
    <section>
      <title>Order Printed Set</title>
      <para>At time of writing you can order the already printed
        game cards and other related material by visiting and
        shopping on http://scrumcardgame.com .</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Print and Play</title>
      <para>This definitively is the more creative approach to get the
        game material. The card designs of the Scrum Card Game are
        available in PDF or even the source format to generate the PDF
        files on your own. If you can get blank business cards available
        as office supplies then you can print the PDF onto the blank
        cards. Another option is to print the cards on normal paper and
        then cut the cards manually. Heavy weight paper shall be used
        for enhanced durability. For better protection the cards could
        be laminated. The lamination foil should be non glare if
        possible and available. In case you plan to create own card 
        texts or modify the existing ones you should go for an
        alternative approach like putting the cards into business
        card pouches for single cards. The cards are kept in the
        protecting pouches while playing and the cards can be easily
        removed from the pouch as intended, be modified and placed
        back.</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="140mm" fileref="media/business_card_pouch.jpg"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Using card size of standard business cards
            (85mm x 54mm) will allow to use business card
            pouches for card protection.</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>Instead of searching for business card pouches in office
        supplies you could find similar articles in game stores
        stocking Trading Card Games (TCGs). TCG players often protect
        their cards with card sleeves or card protectors. The ones
        that match the business cards in size are called
        Standard American Board Game Sleeves (56mm x 87mm).</para>
      <para>More common and popular for TCGs is a so called
        Standard Card Size (88mm x 63mm) with sleeve protectors a bit
        bigger than that (91mm x 66mm). In case you can get these in
        different variants then non glare sleeves are recommended.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>About the Authors</title>
    <section>
      <title>Timofey Yevgrashyn</title>
      <para>I’m an experienced Agile Manager with consulting, coaching
        and training expertise. My personal experience in IT industry
        starts back at 1998, from which more than 12 years I had been
        managing effective software teams and most of the time with
        Agile methods. Over last eight years, I am sharing the knowledge
        and experience as a Trainer, Agile Coach, and Consultant.</para>
      <para>I have proven track record of launching and leading
        Agile/Lean transformations that lead to aligning delivery with
        business goals. By 2016 I have helped to more than 50 teams
        from over 10 countries, done about 3000 hours of Agile training
        for over 4000 people. My specialties: Agile and Lean based
        processes, Agile Product Management, Organizational Culture
        transformation, Leadership Coaching.</para>
      <para>My work is always pragmatic and practical and training is
        more an interactive workshop than just a theory. I’m a big fan
        of education with games and is the author of several
        Agile games.</para>
      <para>Since 2009, I write for my Russian-speaking blog “The
        Improved Methods” (http://tim.com.ua) to popularize Agile/Lean
        mindset and methods on Eastern Europe. Also, I’m an experienced
        public speaker participated in international and local
        conferences. You can find the archive of slides on my site. Or
        simply invite me to your conference for the talk or
        a workshop. :-)</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Oliver Merkel</title>
      <para>I am an Electrical Engineer and Computer Science guy.
        Currently not really in need for any more sophisticated advertising.
        Still if you appreciate my work then tell me or better tell others
        about it. All hands person. Actively developing in embedded systems
        writing boot scripts, boot loaders, hardware abstraction,
        driver development, up to application development and
        architectural stuff in various team sizes and set ups.
        Doing stuff professionally like holding trainings, consulting,
        live agile methods, doing management, project and team leads,
        and developing long enough so to know what I am doing.
        There might be ways to bribe me. Be creative... :-)</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
